Register of the Paul Myron Wentworth Linebarger Papers, 1889-1939
Hoover Institution Archives
Paul Myron Wentworth Linebarger Papers,
1889-1939
82025
Linebarger, Paul Myron Wentworth, 1871-1939.
23 manuscript boxes, 1 album box, 5 envelopes (10.5 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Diaries, correspondence, speeches and writings, notes, printed matter, and photographs, relating to political conditions in China and to Sun Yat-sen.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1982.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Access Points
Sun, Yat-sen, 1866-1925.; China.; China--History--Republic, 1912-1949.; China--Politics and government--1912-1949.
Biographical Note
1871, June 15 Born, Warren, Illinois
1889 Naperville College and Lake Forest University
1889-1892 Law Student, Paris, France
1893 Admitted to Bar, Chicago, Illinois
1893-1895 Student, University of Heidelberg, Germany
1895 Began Law Practice, Chicago, Illinois
1901 Author, Les Combattants Francais
1902 Author, U.S. Government
1901-1907 U.S. Judge, 7th District, Philippine Islands
1907-1925 Legal Adviser to Sun Yat-sen
1912 Married, Lillian Bearden Kirk
1915 Author, Chinese Chances Through Europe's War
1916 Author, Miss American Dollars
1918 Author, This Side of France
1922 Author, The World Gone Mad
1924 Author, Sun Yat-sen and the Chinese Republic
1927 Author, Our Common Cause With China Against Imperialism and Communism
1929 Author, The Maker of Modern China and His Three Principles
1931 Author, La Chin e Navree, Es Espana otra China?
1930-1937 Adviser, Nationalist Government, China
1939, February 20 Died, Washington, D.C.
Container List
- Diaries, 1890-1935. (Box No. 1-4.)
  Diaries and travel journals, arranged in chronological order.
  - 1890 (Box 1., Folder 1)
  - 1891-1892 (Folder 2)
  - 1893 (Folder 3)
  - 1893-1894 (Folder 4)
  - 1895-1896 (Folder 5)
  - 1901-1902 (Box 2., Folder 1)
  - 1902-1903 (Folder 2)
  - 1904 (Folder 3)
  - 1905 (Folder 4)
  - 1906 (Box 3., Folder 1)
  - 1907 (Folder 2)
  - 1914 (Folder 3)
  - 1922 (Folder 4)
  - 1925 (Folder 5)
  - 1929 (Box 4., Folder 1)
  - 1932 (Folder 2)
  - 1933 (Folder 3)
  - 1934-1935 (Folder 4)
- Biographical File, 1910-1938. (Box No. 5-9.)
  Biographical sketches, records, memoranda, and scrapbooks of newspaper clippings and articles related to the career of Paul M.W. Linebarger, arranged by physical form.
  - Address book, 1925 (Box 5., Folder 1)
  - Appointment as Legal Adviser to Nationalist Government, China, 1930 (Folder 2)
  - Biographical data (Folder 3)
  - Calling cards, address lists (Folder 4)
  - Certificates (Folder 5)
  - Clippings (Folder 6-7)
  - Financial records, 1910-1938 - Bank statements, taxes, rent, real estate sales and purchases (Folder 8-13)
  - Medical records (Box 6., Folder 1)
  - Miscellany (Folder 2)
  - Notes - Chinese language study (Folder 3)
  - Passenger lists, programs (Folder 4)
  - Scrapbooks
    - 1918-1919 (Folder 5)
    - 1922-1934 (Folder 6)
    - 1927-1934 (Folder 7)
    - 1930-1934 (Box 7., Folder 1)
    - 1931 (Folder 2)
    - 1931-1934 (Folder 3)
    - 1931-1934 (Folder 4)
    - 1931-1934 (Folder 5)
    - 1927-1935 (Folder 6)
    - 1933-1935 (Folder 7)
    - 1929-1936 (Box 8., Folder 1)
    - 1930-1936 (Folder 2)
    - 1931-1936 (Folder 3)
    - 1931-1936 (Folder 4)
    - 1931-1936 (Folder 5)
    - 1934-1936 (Box 9., Folder 1)
    - 1936 (Folder 2-4)
    - 1933-1937 (Folder 5)
    - 1934-1937 (Folder 6)
    - 1931-1938 (Folder 7)
- Correspondence, 1916-1939. (Box No. 10-11.)
  Arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent.
  - General (Box 10.)
    - 1916 (Folder 1)
    - 1919 (Folder 2)
    - 1920-1922 (Folder 3)
    - 1923 (Folder 4)
    - 1924 (Folder 5)
    - 1925 (Folder 6)
    - 1926-1927 (Folder 7)
    - 1928-1929 (Folder 8)
    - 1930 (Folder 9)
    - 1931 (Folder 10)
    - 1932 (Folder 11)
    - 1933 (Folder 12)
    - 1934-1939 (Folder 13)
  - American Farm Economic Association, 1932 (Box 11., Folder 1)
  - Century Company, 1924 (Folder 2)
  - Cham, H. Hugh, 1930 (Folder 3)
  - Chan, Tom Y., 1931 (Folder 4)
  - Chang, C. C. Cavour, 1930-1933 (Folder 5)
  - Chang Hsueh-liang, 1931 (Folder 6)
  - Chang Nai-yen, 1930 (Folder 7)
  - Chao Chu-wu, 1927 (Folder 8)
  - Chen Chi-tsai, 1933 (Folder 9)
  - Chen, Eugene, n.d. (Folder 10)
  - Chen Kung-po, 1932-1933 (Folder 11)
  - Chen Kuo-fu, 1930-1933 (Folder 12)
  - Chiang Kai-shek, 1933 (Folder 13)
  - Chu, L.W., 1930 (Folder 14)
  - Chu (or Chue), Wander, 1931 (Folder 15)
  - Dunne, William L., 1931 (Folder 16)
  - Fox, Charles J., 1931 (Folder 17)
  - Giles, Herbert A., 1930 (Folder 18)
  - Hashim, N., 1928 (Folder 19)
  - Hu Han-min, 1930 (Folder 20)
  - International Silver Commission, 1930-1931 (Folder 21)
  - Johnson, Nelson T., 1930, 1939 (Folder 22)
  - Koo, Tso-tung, 1933 (Folder 23)
  - Koo, V. K. Wellington, 1932-1933 (Folder 24)
  - Koo Yin-fen, 1930 (Folder 25)
  - Kung, H. H., 1930-1932 (Folder 26)
  - Kwok Bew, 1930 (Folder 27)
  - Lin, Edward Y. T., 1930 (Folder 28)
  - Linebarger, Isaac, 1938 (Folder 29)
  - Linebarger, Lillian (Mrs. P. M. W.), 1937-1938 (Folder 30)
  - Linebarger, Paul Myron Anthony, 1920-1938 (Folder 31)
  - Linebarger, Walter, 1930 (Folder 32)
  - Linebarger, Wayne Wentworth, n.d. (Folder 33)
  - Lloyd, Demarest, 1932 (Folder 34)
  - Mei, Y. C., 1931 (Folder 35)
  - Morgenthau, Henry, Jr., 1933 (Folder 36)
  - Moy, E. K., 1930 (Folder 37)
  - Patel, V., 1932 (Folder 38)
  - San Min Morning Paper, 1931 (Folder 39)
  - Shao Li-tze, 1930 (Folder 40)
  - Soong, T. V., 1930-1933 (Folder 41)
  - Soviet Union Information Bureau, 1931 (Folder 42)
  - Sun Fo, 1928-1933 (Folder 43)
  - Sun Yat-sen, 1924 (Folder 44)
  - Sun Yat-sen, Mme. (Soong Ching-ling), 1921-1924 (Folder 45)
  - Tamm (?), B., 1930 (Folder 46)
  - Thomas, Norman, 1930 (Folder 47)
  - Wang Ching-wei, 1933 (Folder 48)
  - Wang Chung-hui, 1930 (Folder 49)
  - Wu Chao-chu, 1930 (Folder 50)
  - Wu Te-chen, 1932 (Folder 51)
  - Yen, K. S., 1930 (Folder 52)
- Speeches And Writings, 1915-1938. (Box No. 12-20.)
  Manuscripts, notes, drafts, printed copies of the writings of Paul M.W. Linebarger, arranged chronologically.
  - Miscellaneous chapters (Box 12., Folder 1-8)
  - Miscellaneous chapters (Box 13., Folder 1)
  - Miscellaneous notes (Folder 2)
  - "Asia At Our Gates", two carbon copies, n.d. (Folder 3-4)
  - "Bandit-Communist Suppression in China Through Silver Welfare (Min-sheng) Loans", typescript, n.d. (Box 14., Folder 1)
  - "Be True to Your Fate," typescript, n.d. (Folder 2)
  - "China, A Government by Men", carbon copy, n.d. (Folder 3)
  - "China, Irredenta," three carbon copies, n.d. (Folder 4)
  - "China, The Golden West of the Whole World," draft, n.d. (Folder 5)
  - "China's Mixed Courts", one typescript, one carbon copy, n.d. (Folder 6)
  - "Chinese Banks for America Program", one carbon copy, n.d. (Folder 7)
  - "Chinese Interpretative Lyrics", one typescript, one draft, n.d. (Folder 8-9)
  - "Complacent China", one carbon copy, n.d. (Folder 10)
  - "Conversations With Sun Yat-sen", draft, n.d. (Folder 11)
  - "Daniel Dares, A Romance of Travel", typescript, n.d. (Box 15., Folder 1)
  - "Foreign Job Holding in China", carbon copy, n.d. (Folder 2)
  - "The Founder of the Chinese Republic", carbon copy, n.d. (Folder 3)
  - "If Sun Were Still Alive", carbon copy, n.d. (Folder 4)
  - "Jewish and Japanese Trade Morality Compared", carbon copy, n.d. (Folder 5)
  - "A Lawyer's Idle Verse", typescript, n.d. (Folder 6)
  - "Learning Justice From China", carbon copy, n.d. (Folder 7)
  - "Memoir", draft, n.d. (Folder 8-9)
  - "My Eighteen Years As A Disciple of Chung Shan", carbon copy, n.d. (Box 16., Folder 1)
  - "Obstacles of the Unequal Treaties Enough to Frustrate Average Revolutionary Leader", carbon copy, n.d. (Folder 2)
  - "Our Big Sister In China", carbon copy, n.d. (Folder 3)
  - "Our Lost Chance But Not Our Last Chance With China", three carbon copies, n.d. (Folder 4)
  - "Play the Game Square", two printed copies, n.d. (Folder 5)
  - "References to Sun Chung Shan", carbon copy, n.d. (Folder 6)
  - "Strange Murder Case in the Philippines", typescript, n.d. (Folder 7)
  - Verses, drafts and typescripts, n.d. (Folder 8-9)
  - "The Western Jewish Republic", typescript, n.d. (Folder 10)
  - "When Japan Is Ready", two typescript copies, n.d. (Folder 11)
  - "With the American Concentration in the Philippines", typescript, n.d. (Folder 12)
  - "Christian Science, A Tale", typescript and draft, ca. 1915 (Box 17., Folder 1-2)
  - "Miss American Dollars", eight printed advertisements, 1916 (Folder 3)
  - The Chinese Nationalist, two printed copies, magazine edited by Linebarger, December, 1918 (Folder 4)
  - "Chinese Compassion", typescript, 1920 (Folder 5)
  - "Chinese Verses and Other Notes", holograph, ca. 1920 (Folder 6)
  - "The Entourage of Dr. Sun", one typescript, two carbon copies, 1920 (Folder 7)
  - "The Phantom Iceberg", typescript, ca. 1920 (Folder 8)
  - "Chinese Hong Law and Custom", typescript, 1922 (Folder 9)
  - "Sun Yat-sen, Sketches of the Life and Work of the Founder of the Chinese Republic", draft, ca. 1922 (Folder 10)
  - "Sun Yat-sen, Sketches...", carbon copy, ca. 1922 (Box 18., Folder 1)
  - "The World Gone Mad", typescript and carbon, 1922 (Folder 2-3)
  - "Unequal Treaties", typescript, 1923 (Folder 4)
  - "A Family of Five Republics", co-authored with Walter Franklin Lineberger, printed copy, 1925 (Folder 5)
  - Sun Yat-sen, interviews with acquaintances, carbon copy, 1925 (Folder 6)
  - "The International Mixed Court -- Criminal Jurisdiction", carbon copy, 1926 (Folder 7)
  - "What Is The Real Trouble With China Today?", typescript and two carbon copies, 1926 (Folder 8)
  - "Chinese John and the Bible", typescript, 1927 (Folder 9)
  - "The Five Virtues", typescript, 1927 (Folder 10)
  - "Our Common Cause With China Against Imperialism and Communism", printed copy, 1927 (Folder 11)
  - "Chinese Church", holograph, 1929 (Folder 12)
  - "The Faith of the Dare to Dies", typescript, 1929 (Box 19., Folder 1)
  - "Memorial to the Congress of the United States", typescript and carbon copy, 1929 (Folder 2)
  - "Mining Laws of Mexico", processed copy, 1929 (Folder 3)
  - "Chinese Leaders", draft, 1930 (Folder 4)
  - Interview with Linebarger, typescript, 1930 (Folder 5)
  - Message to the Oriental Students Political Association, carbon copy, 1930 (Folder 6)
  - "Sun Yat-sen's Doctrines Make Men Happy, a Religion Without Churches", two carbon copies, 1930 (Folder 7)
  - Testimony Before Special Committee, Communist Activities in the U.S. - House of Representatives, two carbon copies, 1930 (Folder 8)
  - "The American Silver Loan", typescript, ca. 1931 (Folder 9)
  - Interview with Linebarger, typescript, ca. 1931 (Folder 10)
  - "The Laundrymen", address at Miami, Florida, typescript, 1931 (Folder 11)
  - Questionnaire for Womans' Fundamentalist Club, carbon copy, ca. 1931 (Folder 12)
  - Speech on the birthday of Sun Yat-sen, typescript, 1931 (Folder 13)
  - "The World Needs More Silver", carbon copy, 1931 (Folder 14)
  - Academy of World Economics, round table conference on the Manchurian situation, four carbon copies, 1932 (Folder 15)
  - Anniversary ritual services in commemorative honor of Dr. Sun Yat-sen, typescript and two carbon copies, 1932 (Folder 16)
  - Economic conditions in China, carbon copy, 1932 (Folder 17)
  - Fundamentalist League of America Creed, draft and carbon, 1932 (Folder 18)
  - Overseas speeches, carbon copies, 1932 (Folder 19-20)
  - Press releases, typescripts, 1932 (Folder 21)
  - Reports to the Nationalist Government of China, processed copies, 1932-1933 (Folder 22)
  - Sino-Indian Institute for Economic Research, typed copy, 1932 (Folder 23)
  - Sun Yat-sen, article quoting Linebarger in Oriental Revista, printed copy, 1934 (Folder 24)
  - "Les Chansons anniversaires pour Sun Yat-sen", three printed copies, 1935 (Folder 25)
  - "The Gospel of Sun Chung Shan", printed copy, 1935 (Folder 26)
  - "Ocean Men", a play in five acts, typescript, 1935 (Folder 27)
  - "Deutschlands gegenwartige Gelegenheiten in China", printed copy, 1936 (Box 20., Folder 1)
  - "A Follower of Sun Chung Shan", typescript, 1936 (Folder 2)
  - "Sun Yatsens 'San Min Dschu I' und dem deutschen National-Sozialismus", typescript, 1936 (Folder 3)
  - "La Chine et la Judee trop vielles pour mourir, une esquisse des revolutions de Sun Yat-sen", two printed copies, 1937 (Folder 4)
  - "The Ocean Men, an Allegory of the Sun Yat-sen Revolutions", two printed copies, 1937 (Folder 5)
  - "The Ocean Men", draft, 1937 (Folder 6)
  - "Cheerio!... A Century of War Begins", three carbon copies, 1938 (Folder 7)
  - "Mes memoires abreges sur les revolutions de Sun Yat-sen", two printed copies, 1938 (Folder 8)
  - "Tecnique [sic] of the National Government of China", carbon copy, 1938 (Folder 9)
  - "Undermining the Foundation of Government", carbon copy, 1938 (Folder 10)
  - "Work and Hope for China", carbon copy, 1938 (Folder 11)
- Subject File, 1889-1934. (Box No. 21-23.)
  Correspondence, memoranda, printed matter, arranged alphabetically by topic.
  - American Friends of China Association. Membership cards (Box 21., Folder 1)
  - Astronomy. "Climatic conditions on Mars" by W.W. Coblentz, reprinted from Popular Astronomy, May, June and July, 1925 (Folder 2)
  - Baha'i Movement, "What is the Baha'i Movement?", pamphlet, n.d. (Folder 3)
  - China (Folder 4)
    - General
      - The China Critic, February 5, April 9, November 12, November 26, 1931 (Folder 5)
      - The China Review, February, 1932 (Folder 6)
      - China Today, May, August, 1934 (Folder 7)
      - The China Weekly Chronicle, November 6, 13, 20, December 4, 11, 18, 1932, January 8, 1933 (Folder 8)
      - The China Weekly Review, January 10, 24, 31, February 21, 28, March 7, 14, 1931, February 6, 1932 (Folder 9)
      - The Chinese Nation, November 18, 1931 (Folder 10)
      - The Chinese Republic, May 14, July 9, 23, 30, October 29, November 5, December 17, 24, 1932, January 7, 1933 (Folder 11)
      - The Week in China, April 18, August 1, November 14, 21, 28, 1931, January 24, 1932 (Folder 12)
    - Foreign relations (Box 22.)
      - General. "China Firm on Curb of Alien Privileges", clipping, n.d. (Folder 1)
      - United States. Resolution by Linebarger for the 72nd Congress proposing that the outlet for American surpluses be enlarged by selling products to China. (Folder 2)
    - Kuomintang. "Kuomintang Meets at Nanking Today", clipping, n.d. (Folder 3)
    - Legal adviser - correspondence, reports, press releases, 1930-1936 (Folder 4)
    - Legal system. "Data Relating to the Administration of Justice in China" by C.C. Cavour Chang, typescript, ca. 1932 (Folder 5)
    - Miscellany (Folder 6)
    - Politics and government (Folder 7)
      - Government offices and officials
      - Manifesto on the doctrines of Sun Yat-sen
      - National People's Convention, report, January 1, 1931
      - "Three Original Documents from Soviet China", The Provisional Government of the Soviet Republic of China, November 7, 1931
      - "The Triumph of the Nationalists in China" by Roy S. Lautenschlager, Hangchow, 1926
    - Social life and customs (Folder 8)
      - "The Mental or Cultural Phase of Chinese Life Today" by William (?) Allen, February 21, 1932
      - "Soul of China", National Sphere,October, 1930
      - "What the Chinese Are Like", clipping, July 13, 1915
    - War lords. "War Lords Who Struggle for Control of Chaotic China", clipping, April, 12, 1925 (Folder 9)
  - China-America Union (Folder 10)
    - Organization plan
    - Principles and purposes
  - China Institute in America. Pamphlet on founding, board of advisers, officers, purposes, n.d. (Folder 11)
  - Chinese in Mexico. Two copies of La Opinion, Culiacan Rosales, February 16 and 21, 1933, with lead articles on Chinese in Mexico (Folder 12)
  - Chinese in the Philippines. Program of laws, typescript, n.d. (Folder 13)
  - Ethiopia. Correspondence, printed material, 1924-1925 (Folder 14)
  - Language and language study (Folder 15)
    - "The Battle-Line of Languages in Western Europe", by A.L. Guerard, 1923
    - Children's language books for the study of English by Chinese-speaking children
  - Manchurian Incident, 1931 (Folder 16)
    - "Chinese May 'Dig In' At Jehol" clipping, December 17, 1932
    - "Defending Japan in Manchuria", letter to the editor by T.R. Fleming, ca. 1932
    - "Japan Rejects Friendly Advice", clipping, December 14, 1932
    - "Manchuria's Head May Lead Revolt", clipping, ca. 1932
  - Miscellany (Folder 17-18)
  - Philippine Islands - Independence. Memoranda, clippings, reports, printed matter, 1932-1933. (Folder 19)
  - Sun Yat-sen (Box 23.)
    - Autobiography. Six copies in English of How China Was Made a Republic, by Dr. Sun, 1919, with a note by Paul M.A. Linebarger, January 26, 1934 (Folder 1-6)
    - Biographical data (Folder 7)
    - Memorial services (Folder 8)
    - Miscellany (Folder 9)
  - U.S.S.R. Newspaper clipping of column by Eugene Lyons on the Soviet Union, undated (Folder 10)
  - United States
    - Campaign literature, 1889 (Folder 11)
    - Foreign war debts (Folder 12)
    - Legislation and proposed legislation related to China and Japan, 1928-1932 (Folder 13)
- AUDIO-VISUAL., (110 prints / 1 album / 73 book illustrations / 1 album of newspaper clippings, (1901-1906
  - 6 prints of P.M.W. Linebarger; 1 print of C.C> Cavour Chang; 1 print of Ching H. Chi; 1 print of Lucy Estes Linebarger; 1 print of Mme. Sun Yat-sen; 1 print of Dr. and Mrs. Sun Yat-sen; 1 print of Sun Yat-sen; 27 prints of scenes in China, circa 1930 (Folder A)
  - 41 prints of P.M.W Linebarger; 1 campaign photograph, undated (Folder B)
  - 12 prints of P.M.W Linebarger and others, Santiago Chile and Lima, Peru, 1936 (Folder C)
  - 11 unidentified prints, undated (Folder mD)
  - 73 book illustrations, undated (Folder mE)